<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % doc.mod SYSTEM "doc.mod" >
%doc.mod;
]>

<chapter version="5.0"
    xml:id="ws.api"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

<title>C API</title>

<para>There are two APIs in the library: the Client API and the Server API. Both
are built around WebSocket constructs: frames, messages and connections, as you
would expect. Both are designed to be simple and intuitive, managing all the
painful detail work behind the scenes so that you can focus on building the
application. As mentioned in <link linkend="ws.intro">the introduction</link>,
the two APIs are built from completely different networking designs, each suited
to their particular context. The client architecture is designed for single
connections and operates synchronously. The server architecture is designed for
many concurrent connections and operates asynchronously. The client architecture
builds on native operating networking services whereas the server architecture
is built on <filename><link
xlink:href="https://libuv.org/">libuv</link></filename>.</para>

<section id="ws.api.client"><title>The Client API</title>

<section id="ws.api.client.structures"><title>Structures</title>

<para>There are three objects in the C API: connection (<classname><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_cnx</cr></classname>), frame (<classname><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_frame</cr></classname>) and message (<classname><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_msg</cr></classname>). Frames have the following binary
form:

<programlisting>
            /* An RFC 6455 message frame
            **
            **    0                   1                   2                   3
            **    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
            **   +-+-+-+-+-------+-+-------------+-------------------------------+
            **   |F|R|R|R| opcode|M| Payload len |    Extended payload length    |
            **   |I|S|S|S|  (4)  |A|     (7)     |             (16/64)           |
            **   |N|V|V|V|       |S|             |   (if payload len==126/127)   |
            **   | |1|2|3|       |K|             |                               |
            **   +-+-+-+-+-------+-+-------------+ - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
            **   |     Extended payload length continued, if payload len == 127  |
            **   + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +-------------------------------+
            **   |                               | Masking-key, if MASK set to 1 |
            **   +-------------------------------+-------------------------------+
            **   | Masking-key (continued)       |          Payload Data         |
            **   +-------------------------------- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
            **   :                     Payload Data continued ...                :
            **   + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
            **   |                     Payload Data continued ...                |
            **   +---------------------------------------------------------------+
            */
</programlisting>

While frames are a concrete object in the standard, messages are not. Messages
are expressed in terms of frames. Specifically, a message is one or more frames,
terminated by a frame with the <literal>FIN</literal> bit set. So a message can
consist of a single frame with the <literal>FIN</literal> bit set. Alternately,
a message can consist of multiple frames, the last of which has the
<literal>FIN</literal> bet set. In this latter case, the first frame contains
the frame type (<literal>TEXT</literal> or
<literal>BINARY</literal>). Subsequent frames in the chain are of type
<literal>CONTINUATION</literal> (another frame type). The last frame composing
the message will have the <literal>FIN</literal> bit set, signifying the end of
the message. This covers the structural part of the API.</para>

</section> <!-- ws.api.client.structures -->

<section id="ws.api.client.functions"><title>Functions</title>

<para>The functional part of the API operates on these object &mdash;
connections, frames and messages. Thus the functions are divided into three
parts, based on the object they operate on. Of necessity the first object you
must deal with is the connection. You must make a connection before you can send
and receive anything. To this end there is the <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_connect</cr>()</function> <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_disconnect</cr>()</function> functions. You start by
creating a connection object by calling <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_cnx_new</cr>()</function>. Once you have that you can
connect and disconnect. The following illustrates this process:

<sourcecode href="ws.api.client.ex-1.cpp"/>

</para>

<para>The <function><cr f="socket.h">vws_socket_set_timeout</cr>()</function> is
thrown in there for illustration purposes. This is how you can adjust your
timeout value. If you want no timeout at all (blocking indefinitely until
something happens on the socket), you can set the timeout to -1. Additionally,
the <function><cr f="websocket.h">vws_socket_is_connected</cr>()</function> is
the way to tell if your socket is still connected. Should you receive an error
or a timeout when attempting to send or receive, you can use this function to
determine if the connection has been terminated. Finally there is the
<function><cr f="websocket.h">vws_socket_is_connected</cr>()</function> function
which terminates the connection. The connection object can be reused to connect
to another host. If you are done with it then you must call <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_cnx_free</cr>()</function> to free its memory.</para>

<note><title>Windows Timeout Limitation</title>

  <para>There is a limitation to the timeout value of -1 in Windows with respect
  to making connections. The timeout value is used in two places in the code:
  (1) <function>setsockopt()</function> which affects the timeout of connecting
  and (2) in <function>poll()</function> which affects timeout of socket reads
  and writes. Using -1 for <function>poll()</function> works the same on all
  platforms, causing it to block indefinitely. With respect to
  <function>setsockopt()</function>, the code internally sets it to zero when
  making this call to achive blocking. That is to say, when it sees a timeout of
  -1, when calling <function>setsockopt()</function> it must pass it a value of
  zero in order to make the socket blocking in this respect. It makes this
  adjustment internally. However this does not work on Windows. This effectively
  <emphasis>disables</emphasis> blocking. The only solution is to use the
  maximum value which is determined by the Windows <literal>DWORD</literal> type
  &mdash; a signed 32-bit integer. So in the case of Windows when you set the
  timeout to -1, the library internally uses the max <literal>DWORD</literal>
  value (4294967295) which sets the blocking timeout to 136.17 years. So while
  this workaround is limited, should your program need to block for more than
  136.17 years, you will likely not be around to see the bug in practice.</para>

</note>

<para>Next comes messages. The <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_msg_send_text</cr>()</function>, <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_msg_send_binary</cr>()</function>, <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_msg_send_data</cr>()</function> and <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_msg_recv</cr>()</function> deal in messages but work in
terms of frames. The send functions send messages out as a single frame. The
receive function collects incoming frames until it gets one with the
<literal>FIN</literal> bit set. Then it concatenates the data from all frames in
the sequence, forming a single message which it provides as the return
value. The following illustrates using this API to send and receive messages:

<sourcecode href="ws.api.client.ex-2.cpp"/>

</para>

<para>If you need more fine-grained control, you can deal directly in frames if
you need to. There are equivalent functions to send and receive frames:
<function><cr f="websocket.h">vws_frame_send_text</cr>()</function>, <function>
<cr f="websocket.h">vws_frame_send_binary</cr>()</function>, <function> <cr
f="websocket.h">vws_frame_send_data</cr>()</function> and <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_frame_recv</cr>()</function>. The following illustrates
using this API to send and receive frames (which is virtually identical to
messages):

<sourcecode href="ws.api.client.ex-3.cpp"/>

</para>

<para>If you need even more control over that regarding your frame construction,
you can use <function><cr f="websocket.h">vws_frame_send_data</cr>()</function>
and <function><cr f="websocket.h">vws_frame_send</cr>()</function>. The first
function takes data and a frame type, also referred to as the
<literal>opcode</literal> (types are defined in the <classname><cr
f="websocket.h">frame_type_t</cr></classname> enum). This will create a data
frame of that type containing the data passed in and then send it out on the
wire (with the <literal>FIN</literal> bit set). This works for creating single
<literal>TEXT</literal>, <literal>BINARY</literal>, <literal>PING</literal> and
<literal>PONG</literal> frames. However if you want to create a message spanning
multiple frames, you will need to use <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_frame_send</cr>()</function>, which allows you to modify the
frame attributes explicitly to your liking doing things like setting the
<literal>FIN</literal> but to zero. You first create a frame using <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_frame_new</cr>()</function>. Once you have modified the
frame to your liking, you send it out with <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_frame_send</cr>()</function>. The following code illustrates
using these functions to create a message spanning two frames:

<sourcecode href="ws.api.client.ex-4.cpp"/>

</para>

<para>As frames arrive they are put on a receive queue. The <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_frame_recv</cr>()</function> function checks this queue and
returns the first one it finds. If the queue is empty then it intiates a socket
read and waits until the a frame arrives. If no frame arrives within the given
timeout, it will return <literal>NULL</literal>. The <function><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_msg_recv</cr>()</function> function works by the exact same
logic but with messages.

<note><title>Warning: Mixing frame and message functions</title>

  <para>If you use both the frame and message functions together you will need
  to be careful how you use them. If for example you pull a frame off the queue
  via <function><cr f="websocket.h">vws_frame_recv</cr>()</function> and it
  happens to be part of a series of frames composing a message, and then you
  call <function><cr f="websocket.h">vws_msg_recv</cr>()</function> to pull a
  message, you will get a corrupted message because you manually pulled one of
  its frame out off the queue which should have been there as part of the
  message. So if you use both of these functions together you will need to pay
  attention to the frames you pull and take note of the message state based on
  that frame’s type. If you see that that frame is part of a series of frames
  containing a message, then you will need to manually pull the remaining frames
  until you reach the last (<literal>FIN</literal>) frame. Once you are in that
  state then you can resume using <function><cr
  f="websocket.h">vws_msg_recv</cr>()</function> to pull messages as the queue
  is in a consistent state.</para>

</note>

</para>

</section> <!-- ws.api.client.functions -->

<section id="ws.api.client.summary"><title>Summary</title>

<para>That covers the Client API with respect to connections, frames and
messages. Putting it all together, the following example illustrates the basic
usage:

<sourcecode href="ws.api.client.ex-5.cpp"/>

</para>

<para>In summary, what you see here is a synchronous (blocking) client
connection model with an optional timeout. This keeps the API simple and
intuitive. Typically from the client-side this is what you want. The underlying
socket read (<function><cr f="socket.c">vws_socket_read</cr>()</function>) and
write (<function><cr f="socket.c">vws_socket_write</cr>()</function>) operations
are implemented using the operating systems’s <function>poll()</function>
facility, which provides the combination of blocking and timeout. As such, you
can send messages/frames and easily wait for responses to arrive with the option
of a timeout for error detection. Concurrency in this model would be employed
with threads rather than non-blocking I/O. Multiple connections can operate
independently within the threads they are created in. The only limitation is
that a connection should only be used within the thread it was created in, as it
relies on a thread-local variable (<varname>vrtql</varname>) for error handling
and tracing.</para>

</section> <!-- ws.api.client.summary -->

</section> <!-- ws.api.client -->

<section id="ws.api.aux"><title>Common Facilities</title>

<para>The common facilities encompass error handling, memory management, and
tracing. These are consolidated in a thread-local global variable named
<classname><cr f="vrtql.h">vrtql</cr></classname>. As this variable is
thread-local, each thread maintains its independent copy.</para>

<section id="ws.api.aux.errors"><title>Error Handling</title>

<para>Error handling in the API is facilitated through the usage of a code and a
human-readable string. These are encapsulated within an instance of the
<classname><cr f="vrtql.h">vrtql_error_value</cr></classname> structure, kept in
<varname>vrtql.e</varname> member. Error handling is done through the
<function>vrtql.error()</function> and
<function>vrtql.process_error()</function> function pointers. The
<function>vrtql.error()</function> function submits an error for processing and
the <function>vrtql.process_error()</function> takes action on the error. You
can customize both of these handlers by assiging them to different
functions. The default implementation for <function>vrtql.error()</function> is
<function><cr f="vrtql.c">vrtql_error_default_submit</cr>()</function> whereas
the default implementation for <function>vrtql.process_error()</function> is
<function><cr f="vrtql.c">vrtql_error_default_process</cr>()</function>.</para>

</section> <!-- ws.api.aux.errors -->

<section id="ws.api.aux.tracing"><title>Tracing</title>

<para>Tracing is a mechanism for logging debug information and is managed by the
<function>vrtql.trace()</function> function. Tracing outputs log messages
associated with different severity levels (DEBUG, INFO, WARNING, ERROR), with
the level determined by the first parameter of
<varname>vrtql.tracelevel</varname>. The default level is zero which disables
all tracing. Other levels are defined by the <classname><cr
f="message.h">vrtql_tl_t</cr></classname> enum.</para>

</section> <!-- ws.api.aux.tracing -->

<section id="ws.api.aux.memory"><title>Memory Management</title>

<para>The library provides memory management functions that include error
handling mechanisms. These functions are <function>vrtql.malloc()</function>,
<function>vrtql.calloc()</function> and
<function>vrtql.realloc()</function>. These all call the underlying OS functions
but you can provide alternate implementations by assiging new functions.</para>

</section> <!-- ws.api.aux.memory -->
</section> <!-- ws.api.memory -->

<section id="ws.api.msg"><title>The Message API</title>

<para>Working atop the Client API is an optional Message API which provides
additional features for the purpose of creating protocols similar to AMQP and
MQTT. It consists of a specific message structure (<classname><cr
f="message.h">vrtql_msg</cr></classname>) and functions to send (<function><cr
f="message.h">vrtql_msg_send</cr>()</function>) and receive (<function><cr
f="message.h">vrtql_msg_recv</cr>()</function>) it. The message structure
includes two maps (hashtables of string key/value pairs) and a payload. One map,
called <varname>routing</varname>, is designed to hold routing information for
messaging applications. The other map, called <varname>headers</varname>, is for
application use. The payload can hold both text and binary data.</para>

<para>The Message API uses a normal WebSocket connection (<classname><cr
f="websocket.h">vws_cnx</cr></classname>) to send and receive messages in the
same way as the Client API. The only difference is that it deals in
<classname><cr f="message.h">vrtql_msg</cr></classname> objects and
automatically handles serialization and deserialization on and off the
wire. Messages can be serialized in two formats: JSON and MessagePack. Both
formats can be sent over the same connection on a message-by-message basis. That
is, the Message API is able to auto-detect each incoming message’s format and
deserialize accordingly. Thus connections support mixed-content messages: JSON
and MessagePack.</para>

<para>The following is a basic example of using the API.

<sourcecode href="ws.api.aux.msg.ex-1.cpp"/>

</para>

</section> <!-- ws.api.msg -->

<section id="ws.api.server"><title>The Server API</title>

<section id="ws.api.server.arch"><title>Architecture</title>

<para>The server architecture is layered according to the type of data its
handling. The base server works completely on unstructred data. For instance you
could use it to create an echo server, or handle protocols, provided you parse
the data accordingly. The base server is implemented using the <classname><cr
f="server.h">vrtql_svr</cr></classname> struct. Build on top of this is the
WebSocket server (<classname><cr f="server.h">vrtql_ws_svr</cr></classname>). It
works in the same way but deals in WebSocket frames and messages. On top of this
is the messaging server (<classname><cr
f="server.h">vrtql_ws_svr</cr></classname>) which works in terms of Messages
API.</para>


</section> <!-- ws.api.server.arch -->

<section id="ws.api.server.core"><title>Core Server</title>

<para>The core server API is the foundation on which all the other servers
work. Once you understand how it works everything else is intuitive. The API
simple and is designed to make it very each for you to focus on processing
messages. There are only about three things you need to do it create server. You
create server instance, defined a processing function to handle incoming data,
all send data base to the remote peer. We will take each of these in
turn.</para>

<para>You create a server instance the same way as every other object in the
library. In this case you use the <function><cr
f="server.h">vrtql_svr_new</cr>()</function> function. This takes three
arguments: The number of worker threads, the connection backlog, and the maximum
message queue size. If you set the latter two arguments to zero it will use the
defaults. The next thing you do is create a processing funciton. The signature
of this function varies according to server. For the core server, which deals
with unstructured data, this signature is given by the <function><cr
f="server.h">vrtql_svr_process_data</cr></function> callback. It takes a single
argument: a <classname><cr f="server.h">vrtql_svr_data</cr></classname>
instances created on the heap. This structure simply holds a blob of data. You
processing function makes sense of that data and sends whatever data back. The
functions to send data back to the peer is <function><cr
f="server.h">vrtql_svr_send</cr>()</function>. With all these things in place
you call <function><cr f="server.h">vrtql_svr_run</cr>()</function> to start the
server. The following illustrates writing a basic echo server:

<sourcecode href="ws.api.server.core.ex-1.cpp"/>

</para>

</section> <!-- ws.api.server.core -->

<section id="ws.api.server.vws"><title>WebSocket Server</title>

<para>Writing a WebSocket server is even simpler. It follows the same pattern
but uses <function><cr f="server.h">vws_svr_new</cr>()</function> to create the
serve. The processing function signature is given by the <function><cr
f="server.h">vws_svr_process_msg</cr></function> callback. The following
illustates writing a WebSocket server:

<sourcecode href="ws.api.server.vws.ex-1.cpp"/>

</para>

</section> <!-- ws.api.server.vws -->

<section id="ws.api.server.msg"><title>Message Server</title>

<para>The Message API server works in exactly the same way. The following
illustrates creating an instance of it:

<sourcecode href="ws.api.server.msg.ex-1.cpp"/>

</para>

</section> <!-- ws.api.server.msg -->

</section> <!-- ws.api.server -->

<section id="ws.api.rpc"><title>RPC API</title>

<para>

</para>

</section> <!-- ws.api.rpc -->

</chapter> <!-- ws.api -->
