<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % doc.mod SYSTEM "doc.mod" >
%doc.mod;
]>

<chapter version="5.0"
    xml:id="ws.ops"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

<title>Operations</title>

<para>This chapter covers the operational aspects of running VRTQL WebSocket
servers in production environments. It addresses daemonization, configuration,
SSL termination with a reverse proxy, and service management using process
supervisors.</para>

<section id="ws.ops.config"><title>Daemons and Configuration</title>

<para>A VRTQL WebSocket server is a long-running process that listens for
incoming connections on a configured host and port. In production, these servers
typically run as daemons &mdash; background processes detached from any
controlling terminal. There are two common approaches to daemonizing a VRTQL
server: using the traditional <function>fork()</function>/<function>setsid()
</function> pattern within the program itself, or delegating process management
to an external supervisor (covered in <link linkend="ws.ops.perpd">Service
Management</link>). The latter approach is generally preferred as it provides
better control over the process lifecycle.</para>

<para>When running a server as a daemon, the server's host, port, number of
worker threads, and other parameters are typically read from a configuration
file or environment variables at startup. While the VRTQL library itself does
not mandate a particular configuration format, a common approach is to use a
simple key-value configuration file or environment variables. The following
illustrates a minimal configuration pattern:

<programlisting>
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;
#include &lt;vws/server.h&gt;

int main(int argc, const char* argv[])
{
    // Read configuration from environment or defaults
    cstr host    = getenv("VWS_HOST") ? getenv("VWS_HOST") : "0.0.0.0";
    int  port    = getenv("VWS_PORT") ? atoi(getenv("VWS_PORT")) : 8181;
    int  threads = getenv("VWS_THREADS") ? atoi(getenv("VWS_THREADS")) : 10;

    // Create and configure server
    vrtql_msg_svr* server = vrtql_msg_svr_new(threads, 0, 0);
    server->process       = my_process_handler;

    // Run (blocks until server is stopped)
    vrtql_msg_svr_run(server, host, port);

    // Cleanup
    vrtql_msg_svr_free(server);
    vws_cleanup();

    return 0;
}
</programlisting>

</para>

<para>The server binds to the specified host and port and begins accepting
connections. Binding to <literal>0.0.0.0</literal> makes the server accessible
on all network interfaces, whereas <literal>127.0.0.1</literal> restricts it to
local connections only. In production deployments behind a reverse proxy, binding
to <literal>127.0.0.1</literal> is recommended so that external traffic is
directed through the proxy.</para>

<para>The number of worker threads should be tuned based on the workload. For
I/O-bound processing (such as database queries), more threads can be beneficial.
For CPU-bound processing, the number of threads should generally match the
number of available CPU cores. The connection backlog and queue size parameters
can typically be left at their defaults unless the server is expected to handle a
very high rate of incoming connections or messages.</para>

<para>The server also supports an <firstterm>inetd mode</firstterm> via the
<function><cr f="server.h">vws_tcp_svr_inetd_run</cr>()</function> function.
In this mode, the server does not bind to a port itself. Instead, an external
program such as <command>tcpserver</command> (from the
<filename>ucspi-tcp</filename> package) accepts the connection and passes the
open file descriptor to the server. This is useful for deployments that prefer
to delegate connection acceptance to an external tool.</para>

</section> <!-- ws.ops.config -->

<section id="ws.ops.haproxy"><title>HAProxy and SSL Termination</title>

<para>In production, it is common practice to terminate SSL/TLS connections at a
reverse proxy rather than in the application server itself. This approach
offloads the computational overhead of encryption to dedicated infrastructure,
simplifies certificate management, and allows the backend server to operate over
plain (unencrypted) WebSocket connections. <link
xlink:href="https://www.haproxy.org/">HAProxy</link> is a widely used, high-
performance reverse proxy that supports WebSocket connections natively.</para>

<para>A typical deployment places HAProxy in front of one or more VRTQL
WebSocket servers. HAProxy accepts incoming <literal>wss://</literal>
connections from clients, terminates the SSL/TLS session, and forwards the
traffic to the backend server as plain <literal>ws://</literal> connections.
The VRTQL server binds to <literal>127.0.0.1</literal> on a non-public port,
and only HAProxy is exposed to the public network.</para>

<para>The following is a minimal HAProxy configuration that demonstrates this
setup:

<programlisting>
global
    maxconn 4096

defaults
    mode    http
    timeout connect  5s
    timeout client  30s
    timeout server  30s
    timeout tunnel  3600s

frontend wss_frontend
    bind *:443 ssl crt /etc/ssl/private/server.pem
    default_backend ws_backend

backend ws_backend
    server vrtql1 127.0.0.1:8181 check
</programlisting>

</para>

<para>The key configuration directives are as follows:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The <literal>bind *:443 ssl crt</literal> directive in the
frontend section tells HAProxy to listen on port 443 and terminate SSL using the
specified certificate file. The certificate file should contain both the
certificate and private key in PEM format.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <literal>timeout tunnel</literal> directive is critical for
WebSocket connections. Unlike standard HTTP requests which are short-lived,
WebSocket connections are long-lived. This timeout governs how long HAProxy will
keep an idle tunnel (upgraded connection) open. Set it to a value appropriate for
your application &mdash; 3600 seconds (one hour) is a reasonable starting
point.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The backend <literal>server</literal> directive points to the
VRTQL server's host and port. The <literal>check</literal> option enables health
checks.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>For deployments with multiple backend servers, HAProxy can load-balance
across them:

<programlisting>
backend ws_backend
    balance roundrobin
    server vrtql1 127.0.0.1:8181 check
    server vrtql2 127.0.0.1:8182 check
    server vrtql3 127.0.0.1:8183 check
</programlisting>

</para>

<para>Note that WebSocket connections are stateful, so sticky sessions
(session affinity) may be required depending on your application's design. You
can enable this in HAProxy using cookies or source IP hashing via the
<literal>balance source</literal> directive.</para>

</section> <!-- ws.ops.haproxy -->

<section id="ws.ops.perpd"><title>Service Management</title>

<para>In production environments, server processes should be managed by a
process supervisor that can start, stop, and automatically restart the service
if it exits unexpectedly. Several options are available on Unix-like systems,
including <command>perpd</command>, <command>systemd</command>,
<command>runit</command>, and <command>s6</command>. This section covers
<command>perpd</command> and <command>systemd</command> as representative
examples.</para>

<section id="ws.ops.perpd.perpd"><title>Using perpd</title>

<para><link xlink:href="http://b0llix.net/perp/">perpd</link> is a lightweight
process supervisor that monitors a set of services defined as directories under
a base path (typically <filename>/etc/perp</filename>). Each service directory
contains a <filename>rc.main</filename> script that starts and stops the
service. The supervisor will automatically restart the service if it
terminates.</para>

<para>To set up a VRTQL server as a <command>perpd</command> service, create
a service directory and its control script:

<screen>
<prompt>#</prompt> mkdir -p /etc/perp/vrtql-ws
</screen>

</para>

<para>Then create the <filename>/etc/perp/vrtql-ws/rc.main</filename> script:

<programlisting>
#!/bin/sh

exec 2>&amp;1

TARGET=${1}

start()
{
    exec /usr/local/bin/vrtql-ws-server
}

reset()
{
    exit 0
}

eval ${TARGET} "$@"
</programlisting>

</para>

<para>Make the script executable and activate the service:

<screen>
<prompt>#</prompt> chmod +x /etc/perp/vrtql-ws/rc.main
<prompt>#</prompt> perpctl A vrtql-ws
</screen>

</para>

<para>The service can be controlled using <command>perpctl</command>:

<screen>
<prompt>#</prompt> perpctl d vrtql-ws   # stop (down)
<prompt>#</prompt> perpctl u vrtql-ws   # start (up)
<prompt>#</prompt> perpstat vrtql-ws    # check status
</screen>

</para>

</section> <!-- ws.ops.perpd.perpd -->

<section id="ws.ops.perpd.systemd"><title>Using systemd</title>

<para>On systems using <command>systemd</command>, you can create a unit file
to manage the VRTQL server. Create
<filename>/etc/systemd/system/vrtql-ws.service</filename>:

<programlisting>
[Unit]
Description=VRTQL WebSocket Server
After=network.target

[Service]
Type=simple
ExecStart=/usr/local/bin/vrtql-ws-server
Restart=always
RestartSec=5
Environment=VWS_HOST=127.0.0.1
Environment=VWS_PORT=8181
Environment=VWS_THREADS=10

[Install]
WantedBy=multi-user.target
</programlisting>

</para>

<para>Enable and start the service:

<screen>
<prompt>#</prompt> systemctl daemon-reload
<prompt>#</prompt> systemctl enable vrtql-ws
<prompt>#</prompt> systemctl start vrtql-ws
<prompt>#</prompt> systemctl status vrtql-ws
</screen>

</para>

<para>The <literal>Restart=always</literal> directive ensures that
<command>systemd</command> will automatically restart the server if it exits for
any reason. The <literal>RestartSec=5</literal> directive adds a five-second
delay before restarting, which prevents rapid restart loops in the event of a
persistent failure.</para>

</section> <!-- ws.ops.perpd.systemd -->

</section> <!-- ws.ops.perpd -->

</chapter>
